Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan

sviswa10@asu.edu | 480-399-3390 | linkedin.com/in/sreeaurovindh | Portfolio: folio.sreeml.com |

Summary

Computer Science Ph.D. Candidate with a strong background in machine learning, big data analytics, software development and statistics. Five years of professional experience in building machine learning models with Scientific Python Stack, R and have worked on extensive independent data science projects

Education

Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science

May 2020

Arizona State University, Tempe. (GPA 3.70/4.00)

Master of Science, Computer Science

Aug 2014

Arizona State University, Tempe. (GPA 3.52/4.00)

Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science

May 2010

Anna University, Tamilnadu, India. (GPA 78/100)

Skills

Machine Learning and Statistical Modelling: Classification, clustering, regression model selection, ensemble methods, neural networks and support vector machines

Experimental Design: Multi Arm bandit tests, Hypothesis Testing and Metric Evaluation

Big data Technology: Map Reduce (Hadoop), Apache Airflow, ETL (Pig and Hive), AWS and GCP

Scientific Python Stack: Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn and Jupyter Notebooks **Programming Languages and Databases:** Python, R, Java, PHP, SQL, MySQL and MongoDB

Patents

Systems and methods for estimating an impact of changing a source file in a software (US9201649B2) Methods, systems and computer-readable media for detecting a partial commit (US9785430B2)

Professional Experience

Data Scientist Intern

May 2019 - Aug 2019

Slack Technologies, San Francisco, United States

- Designed and implemented large scale graph models to understand usage of Slack across organizations
- Worked as a part of Quantitative Research team to generate reliable insights on user communication

Data Scientist Intern

June 2018 – Aug 2018

Pandora Media, Oakland, United States

- Developed and implemented various machine learning models for helping 36% (18 M) of Pandora's listeners to start a music station they would prefer at the beginning of the listener session
- Designed multi arm bandit experiment to validate the impact of the recommended station across Pandora's listener base

Graduate Research Assistant

Dec 2012- Present

Arizona State University, Tempe, United States

- Hypothesized and established different qualitative levels of collaborative human behavior after careful analysis of over 130+ hours of observational study involving student's work on digital tablets
- Developed supervised and unsupervised models that classified quality of user interactions between student pairs using data from a combination of interaction logs and acoustic and prosodic fingerprint
- Performed feature engineering in R using log features and extracted time-series based features using raw audio data using scientific Python Stack that improved balanced accuracy (BAC) 15% above baseline
- Created privacy preserving collaboration detectors that uses superficial audio features to classify student collaboration behavior

System Engineer (Research)

June 2010- Jul 2012

Software Engineering and Technology Labs, Infosys Labs, Bangalore, India

- Designed and developed bug prediction system which provided various metrics that enabled product managers to gauge the release readiness of the software system
- Clustered millions of commit data and developer profiles using Java and SQL based on their source code version history to provide better resource allocation to various bug fixes

Data Science Projects

Experimentation to Evaluate and Enhance Student Experience

Aug 2017 – Dec 2017

- Accessible at folio.sreeml.com
- Evaluated various invariant and evaluation metrics to measure the effect of the screening test
- Estimated number of samples and statistical power required to conduct a randomized trial
- Assessed the impact of trial screener on student experience using effect size, significance and sign tests
- Recommended a follow up to reduce early cancellations by measuring total number of hours spent

Yelp Food Recommender

Jan 2017- Sept 2017

Accessible at yelp.sreeml.com

- Mapped Yelp user reviews to specific food items by combining data from Yelp and Wikipedia by performing text search on Yelp reviews using Apache Solr
- Created a dashboard that compares quality of food items of different restaurants in a specific neighborhood and enabled business owners to understand food quality changes over time

Search for Sensitive Information in Enron Email Corpus

July 2017- Aug 2017

- Accessible at cluster.sreeml.com

 Clustered emails based on dense vector representations of words learned by Word2Vec model and
- evaluated quality obtained by various algorithms using Silhouette Coefficient
- Uncovered five high level categories of emails that contains sensitive information such as credit card numbers and bank account information and flagged them for careful analysis

Data Exploration and Recommendation System

Jan 2015- May 2015

- Created a recommendation system that predicts the expert user who would likely answer the question along with the reasonable time estimate from a corpus of over 2 million posts
- Developed code in R and Python in order to perform preprocessing of data by using standard Natural language processing techniques and calculated TF-IDF score for each term in the document
- Extracted cosine similarity across the entire document corpus to find documents with similar characteristics using Apache Mahout and Amazon web services

Publications

Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan, and Kurt VanLehn. "Detection of collaboration: Relationship between Log and Speech-Based Classification." International conference on Artificial Intelligence in Education. 2019

Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan, and Kurt VanLehn. "Collaboration detectors that preserves the privacy of students' speech." International conference on Artificial Intelligence in Education. Springer, Cham 2019

Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan, and Kurt VanLehn. "High Accuracy Detection of Collaboration from Log Data and Superficial Speech Features." International Society on Learning Sciences 2017.

Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan, and Kurt VanLehn. "Using the tablet gestures and speech of pairs of students to classify their collaboration." IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies (2017)

Girish Makseri Rama, Deepthi Karnam, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Srinivas Padmanabamuni, "Bug Prediction Metrics based decision support for Preventive software maintenance", Software Engineering Conference(APSEC) 2012, 2012 19th Asia- Pacific

Girish Maskeri Rama, Deepthi Karnam, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Srinivas Padmanabamuni,"Version history based source code plagiarism detection in proprietary systems", 2012 28th IEEE International conference on Software Maintenance(ICSM), pp.609-612

G Shankar, **Sree Aurovindh Viswanathan**, Gowthamie B, "Swarm based intelligent transition of control from Manned to Unmanned vehicular system using Sun SPOT", International Journal of Computer Applications, February 2010, Volume I, 82-89